Alright, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today we are on דף נ"ו, Daf
Nun Vav, 56, the last דף Daf of the fifth פרק, Perek,
but we start on דף נ"ה עמוד ב' Daf Nun He Amud
Bet about 15 lines from the bottom at the two dots, which
says ראובן בני עלי בני שמואל דוד ושלמה ויואש. Reuven Bnei Eli
Bnei Shmuel David veShlomo veYoash. So that's a nice little summary of
all the people who it seems like they sinned, although יואש Yoash
may be the least of them, but anyway, and we're going to
be told that they actually did not sin. And we started this
yesterday with ראובן, Reuven,
and actually ראובן Reuven we're not going to discuss today, it's referring
to what we did yesterday, that anybody says ראובן Reuven sinned is
only making a mistake, but the גמרא, Gemara, right, but the גמרא
Gemara very explicitly said that actually that was a matter of debate.
So now that's important to remember, it's not like this is the
unanimous position of the גמרא. Gemara. So now we continue in that
vein. Okay, and yesterday was רבי שמואל בר נחמני Rabbi Shmuel bar
Nachmani in the name of רבי יונתן, Rabbi Yonatan, and that is
the same one who is continuing today. אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני
אמר רבי יונתן כל האומר בני עלי חטאו אינו אלא טועה. Amar
Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan kol ha'omer bnei Eli chat'u
eino ela to'eh. Whoever says the sons of עלי Eli sinned is
only making a mistake, שנאמר, shene'emar, right, עלי Eli was the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol there before and then
and then what? Before שמואל, Shmuel, thank you, right, with חנה. Chana.
ושם שני בני עלי חפני ופנחס כהנים לה', Vesham shnei bnei Eli
Chofni uPhinehas Kohanim LaHashem, and there were the two sons of עלי,
Eli, חפני Chofni and פנחס, Phinehas, כהנים לה'. Kohanim LaHashem.
And if you keep on reading it sounds like they actually were
abusing their power, the religious powers of their religious position, and using
it to as a way of sleeping with women and other types
of things which sadly those types of phenomena are still with us.
So how do you what do you do with the פסוקים? Pesukim?
So the גמרא Gemara says סבר לה כרב, savar lah k'Rav, he
holds like רב, Rav, דאמר רב פנחס לא חטא, d'amar Rav Pinchas
lo chata, as רב Rav said, פנחס Phinehas did not sin. We're
going to argue in a minute that פנחס Phinehas didn't sin, this
פנחס, Phinehas, not the other פנחס. Phinehas. And once you can prove
that פנחס Phinehas didn't sin, then מקיש חפני לפנחס, makish Chofni lePhinehas,
it compares חפני Chofni to פנחס. Phinehas. מה פנחס לא חטא אף
חפני לא חטא. Mah Pinchas lo chata af Chofni lo chata. Just
as פנחס Phinehas didn't sin, חפני Chofni didn't sin. אלא מה אני
מקיים, Ela mah ani mekayem, so what do I do with the
passage that the פסוק Pasuk says אשר ישכבון את הנשים, asher yishkvun
et hanashim, that they slept with the women who were coming to
bring their sacrifices? So the גמרא Gemara says מתוך ששהו את קיניהן,
mitoch sheshiheu et kineihen, because they delayed bringing their bird sacrifices when
they had given birth, childbirth or other types of קרבנות Korbanot that
the women would bring, primarily childbirth would be the most common. שלא
הלכו אצל בעליהן, shelo halchu ezel ba'alehen,
and now actually before you bring your sacrifice a woman is still
permitted to her husband, that doesn't determine the טומאה Tum'ah וטהרה veTaharah
vis-a-vis the husband, it determines whether she's fully טהורה Tehorah in order
to enter into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and eat sacrifice, but
nevertheless you're there, you're waiting for your sacrifice to be brought and
they're dilly-dallying around and you have to wait till the next day,
you're not going home till the next day, so they delayed them
and they were not sleeping with their husbands. מעלה עליהן הכתוב כאילו
שכבו עמן, Ma'aleh aleihen HaKatuv ke'ilu shachvu iman, the תורה Torah treats
it as if they slept with these women because they in a
way got in between these women and their husbands by preventing the
women from going back to their husbands that night. So on the
one hand, obviously, and I'll talk about this more in a minute,
it's to the idea of somehow trying to excuse
what the תורה Torah seems to be very much
indicting them for this sin and trying to find a way to
excuse it raises other very serious problems. And one, maybe I'll talk
about it now. What we're going to be discussing all of today
is this person didn't really sin, that person didn't really sin, and
a lot of these sins actually a lot of them are sexual
sins, by the way. We have ראובן, Reuven, we have בני עלי,
Bnei Eli, we're going to have דוד, David, you're going to have
שמואל, Shmuel, I mean שלמה, Shlomo, excuse me. So a lot of
these are sexual sins. So first of all that's again like אין
כל חדש תחת השמש, ein kol chadash tachat hashemesh, people in positions
of like religious authority can use it as opportunities
for, can sometimes use this as a way of abuse and of
sexual abuse and of opportunities, so that's obviously a real issue that's
still with us. But then the גמרא Gemara goes and tries to
find a way to say well, it didn't really mean it, what
it really means is that they did something that was really bad
and it's as if they did this
thing. So I really struggled with this approach that we're going to
be seeing all of today for two reasons. First of all the
פשט Pshat of the פסוקים Pesukim is not that. אין מקרא יוצא
מידי פשוטו, Ein mikra yotze miyedei pshuto, so it's important to note
that many great rabbis have felt that you don't have to take
what the גמרא Gemara is saying as literal. But even but also,
part of the message that reading the פסוקים כפשוטם Pesukim kiphshutam shows
you that even great people
can sin and that the greatness is how do you deal with
sin and how do you deal with תשובה, Teshuvah, and we don't
have to have an unrealistic picture of what it means to be
a religious person or striving to be a religious person. So the
question is... If when we paint everybody in an ideal light, you
know, how does that what's the positive benefit of that? That holds
up a religious model that is unattainable and therefore is it really
something that is helpful and instructive for us? So that's like one
question I have. Now I suppose an answer to that could be,
you know, it's very nice to see that these are very holy
religious people that have sinned, but the opposite concern is you'll say,
oh, so they're nothing special, you know, they sin, I sin, whatever,
so you know and it could lead to the opposite extreme. So
maybe this is a little bit restoring the balance, trying to hold
them up as complete ideals so at least you have some healthy
balance between that sense of them as holy religious people and at
the same time as people that could slip and err. So that's
I guess one positive point, but I do see that there's this
concern about making them an ideal that's unattainable, but the bigger concern
I have is that it sort of, you know, is that it
signals this idea that if it looks like somebody has done this
terrible thing, they couldn't have done this terrible thing, they're such a
religious person, so let's find some way to explain it away and
say it didn't really happen. And you know, that I just think
is something that is very dangerous, it's always been dangerous, dangerous particularly
nowadays as we see that this issue of sexual abuse by people
in positions of religious power is a very, you know, serious issue.
So I'm just putting that on the table that I, you know,
that I really struggled with, you know, the takeaway from all of
this. One positive thing I will say that does come out from
this גמרא Gemara though about the way it redefines the sin of
חפני Chofni and פנחס Pinchas and maybe this is the most sort
of positive that emerges is that similar to the גמרא Gemara of
yesterday that spoke about that if you are in a position to
protest and you don't protest, then, you know, you're held accountable, what
it does is that it creates a high level of accountability for
even lesser sins, for even lesser, you know, and therefore by saying
that if they, you know, postpone the sacrifice, it's as if they
slept with the women, well if you take that seriously, then it
means that not only are you not allowed to do the obvious
sins, but even things that are, you know, that are minor. And
you know, this becomes an important question, like when we teach הלכות
נידה Hilchos Niddah to the guys in the ישיבה, Yeshiva, the idea
of what it means to give somebody a timely response when it's
about the ability of husband and wife to be together, what it
means
to not be the reason that husband and wife have to be
apart, and the weight in which it's assigned in this גמרא, Gemara,
מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו שכבם, Ma’aleh Alav Hakasuv K’ilu Shachvam, is a
very important message. So I mean that I think would be like
the message I'd like to focus on, that sort of weight of
responsibility that it creates on leaders and how even small things can
become magnified, but I did want to really put on right from
the outset that it raises definitely certain very, you know, I think
very important challenges. Yeah, Charlie, and then.
This actually could have been one of the examples of that because
in the נביא Navi it says, חפץ ה׳ להמיתם Chafetz Hashem L’hamitam
about the sons, and then the very next chapter עלי Eli is
told that his family's hold on the priesthood is going to be
removed because עלי Eli didn't protest.
Oh, you mean because עלי, Eli, you could have focused on עלי’ס
Eli’s silence. That is true in terms of the earlier גמרא Gemara
about anybody who didn't protest. Yeah, that's a very good point.
Yeah, Michael has two questions on that. You know, one is like,
I mean, probably half, I mean, saying that without basis, but I
would say most people haven't really even heard of חפני Chofni and
פנחס. Pinchas. So to say that these are like, you know, religious
role models that we all look up to and, you know, in
a sense I understand explaining ראובן Reuven away.
Yeah, I agree with you. I thought the same thing. I mean
to say ראובן, Reuven, דוד, Dovid, שלמה, Shlomo, you want to hold
them up as some type of a religious ideal and try to
create that sense of, right, but like בני עלי? Bnei Eli? Fine,
who cares?
Right? Right? And then there’s like a debate yesterday where there were
those opinions that said he really did sin. You know, here we're
trying to say they really didn't sin. In other words, why did
some say, yeah, no, they sinned, and others say, no, they didn't
sin?
Right, I know, so I understand. Yeah, well that's true, I mean
why do we only hear the protest by ראובן? Reuven? I would
like to assume that that protest should be translated into all of
the rest as
well. Exactly.
Otherwise I disagree with Michael. They were very important in their time.
They were the chief religious leaders. They were sitting there in the
משכן. Mishkan.
For עלי Eli anyway.
And then his sons when the צובאות Tzove’ot came, that it’s as
it says who were abused by them, they were, they were there.
They were
there.
I know, but Michael's sort of saying in the religious historical consciousness
of us, not in terms of the story at the time. They
knocked them out! Because of their sin!
Because God
knocked, God knocked
them out!
So it actually raises an interesting thread here that all but דוד
Dovid attained their position because they were sons of someone. ראובן Reuven
was the son of יעקב, Yaakov, בני עלי, Bnei Eli, שלמה Shlomo
was the son of דוד. Dovid. That's how they attained their position.
Aha. That's interesting.
I don't know what to make about that.
Okay, that's interesting.
Not יואש, Yoash, but יואש Yoash was like the lightest of the
bunch. Okay. So with all that being said, let's see now as
the גמרא Gemara continues. גופא. Gufa. אמר רב. Amar Rav.
Exactly what this is and according to גמרא Gemara they delayed,
they delayed bringing the sacrifices of women so the women couldn't go
home with their husbands.
They delayed bringing the sacrifices. So what did they?
They said oh, get to it tomorrow, we're very busy today, I
can't be bothered right now.
Why the delay?
If someone brings you, it's a live animal, it hasn't been שחט
shechted yet. So put it there, take a number, we'll get to
you.
But then the women had to wait there until they did it.
Right.
Right. And in the very next chapter, the very next verse, God
is criticizing for doing that, says they're going to die and then
they...
Right, right, right, but יהושע Yehoshua just wants to understand the way
the גמרא Gemara is framing it. Right, correct.
Right, they were bad guys.
Right, that the גמרא Gemara is not denying, but it's making it...
right, right, but the גמרא Gemara is reframing it as because they
were more of a sin of omission than of commission, because they
were just lazy and didn't get to it in time and whatever,
then they're treated as if they actually committed adultery.
But you know it doesn't, it totally doesn't hold up according to
פשט. Pshat.
והשכבות V'hashochvot who stayed
there, השכבות hashochvot are the women who hung out there.
So it didn't make... I get it, I get it, nobody is
denying that it's not פשט, Pshat, that's why I said right at
the outset. But yeah, alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: גופא, Gufa, let's look at the original statement. אמר רב פנחס
לא חטא, Amar Rav Pinchas lo chata, so the way we get
that חפני Chofni didn't sin is by thinking פנחס Pinchas didn't sin.
How do we know פנחס Pinchas didn't sin? שנאמר ואחיה בן אחיטוב
אחי איכבוד בן פנחס בן עלי כהן ה׳. Shenemar V'Achiyah ben Achituv
achi Ichavod ben Pinchas ben Eli kohen Hashem. So this certain person
who's the son of אחיטוב Achituv who is brother of איכבוד, Ichavod,
the son of, anyway, the son of פנחס. Pinchas. So this אחיה
Achiyah was the grandson of פנחס בן עלי כהן ה׳. Pinchas ben
Eli kohen Hashem. אפשר חטא בא לידו והכתוב מיחסו? Efshar chata ba
l'yado v'hakatuv meyachaso? Is it possible that פנחס Pinchas did this terrible
sin and אחיה's Achiyah being sort of, you know, who's a good
guy, is being given this יחוס yichus back to פנחס? Pinchas? You
wouldn't have mentioned him if he was a רשע. rasha. והלא כבר
נאמר יכרת ה׳ לאיש אשר יעשנה ער ועונה מאהלי יעקב ומגיש מנחה
לה׳ צבאות. V'halo kvar neemar yichrat Hashem la'ish asher ya'asennah er v'oneh
me'oholei Yaakov umagish minchah l'Hashem tzevaot. So this is the punishment that
this is what it says to somebody who commits the sin of
adultery. God will wipe out that person. This is not from שמואל,
Shmuel, this is from מלאכי. Malachi. Will wipe out the person who
will do this. ער ועונה, Er v'oneh, you know, means that they'll
be like childless from the tents of יעקב Yaakov and to bringing
a מנחה minchah to God. אם ישראל הוא, Im Yisrael hu, if
he's a ישראל, Yisrael, meaning not a כהן, kohen, לא יהיה לו
ער בחכמים ולא עונה בתלמידים. lo yiheyeh lo er bachachamim v'lo oneh
b'talmidim. He will not have an awareness, like a presence among the
sages or a period amongst the students. So he's reading ער ועונה
er v'oneh not as childless, not as ערירי, ariri, but as a
presence, he will not have a presence in the בתי מדרש. batei
midrash. ואם כהן הוא, V'im kohen hu, if he's a כהן, kohen,
לא יהיה לו בן מגיש מנחה. lo yiheyeh lo ben magish minchah.
He will not have a son that will bring a מנחה minchah
to God. So if פנחס Pinchas did this sin of adultery, how
could אחיה Achiyah be bringing a מנחה minchah and be being a
כהן kohen and how would the פסוק pasuk have, you know, have
made this יחוס yichus of his grandfather פנחס Pinchas if, you know,
this should have been the consequence of the sin. אלא לאו שמע
מינה פנחס לא חטא. Ela lav shema minah Pinchas lo chata. It
must be פנחס Pinchas didn't really sin. אלא הכתיב ישכבון? Ela hachtiv
yishkevuun? How? It doesn't say ישכבון, yishkevuun, so before we said it
meant they didn't really sleep, they postponed. But here רב Rav is
saying no, פנחס Pinchas didn't sin, חפני Chofni sinned. So ישכבן כתיב.
yishkevan ktiv. So don't read it in the plural, read it in
the singular. So according to רב, Rav, חפני Chofni did sin. But
it's only שמואל בר נחמני Shmuel bar Nachmani who says that neither
of them sinned.
The sin of delaying, not necessarily sleeping.
Oh, according to רב, Rav, חפני Chofni did the sin that was
attributed. It's only שמואל בר נחמני Shmuel bar Nachmani that reinterprets it
for both of them. והכתיב
אל בני כי לא טובה השמועה, V'hachtiv al banai ki lo tovah
hashemuah, my sons. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק בני כתיב. Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak beni ktiv. That's an easy one. והכתיב מעבירים, V'hachtiv
ma'avirimm, that they, you know, that what's the
פסוק... pasuk... מה פסוק מעבירים... mah pasuk ma'avirimm... I'm just hold on...
you've got it...
what does it say? Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says anyway it's
in plural, so אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע מעבירם כתיב. Amar
Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua ma'aviram ktiv. It doesn't say... it says
it מעבירם ma'aviram in the singular, it's written without a יוד. yud.
הכתיב אל בני כי לא טובה השמועה אשר אנכי שומע מעבירים עם
ה׳. Hachtiv al banai ki lo tovah hashemuah asher anochi shome'a ma'avirimm
am Hashem. מעבירים
עם ה׳.
Ma'avirimm am Hashem.
So they transgressed God. Okay, thanks. So it's the end of the
פסוק. pasuk. והכתיב בני בליעל. V'hachtiv bnei beliya'al.
Actually it does have a יוד yud in there, מעבירים. ma'avirimm.
I know, I'm going to talk about that in a minute. והכתיב
בני בליעל. V'hachtiv bnei beliya'al. Doesn't it say, you know, "sons of
rebellious sons"? So again, that could be בני בליעל, bnei beliya'al, but
it doesn't work because it's not "my son", it's סמיכות. smichut. So
if we're singular it would have to be בן בליעל, ben beliya'al,
right? So it says בני בליעל. bnei beliya'al. So, back to the
earlier theme: מתוך שהיה לו לפנחס למחות בחפני ולא מיחה מעלה עליו
הכתוב כאילו חטא. Mitoch shehayah lo l'Pinchas limchot b'Chofni v'lo michah ma'aleh
alav hakatuv k'ilu chata. So פנחס Pinchas could have intervened, פנחס Pinchas
could have protested. So according to רב Rav it's not such a
whitewash. According to רב, Rav, חפני Chofni really did it and פנחס
Pinchas is held responsible because he could have protested. Okay, and it's
also important then in the context of רב, Rav, the argument that
פנחס Pinchas couldn't do it is that somebody that actually does it,
quoting the פסוק pasuk in מלאכי, Malachi, the punishment would have been,
you know, extremely severe. So he's not ruling out the possibility that
people could do it, just says פנחס Pinchas didn't, but חפני Chofni
did, but quoting that פסוק pasuk in מלאכי, Malachi, you know, is
very important in terms of like I think this attitude of not
you know... denying the possibility that this type of a thing can
and does happen. Now, an interesting point that it says מעבירם, Ma'aviram,
and the גמרא's Gemara answer is that it's written without a יוד,
Yud, so רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot are both bothered by this.
If you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says the three-four lines
from the bottom, קשה בעיני שמכח המקרא הנזכר כאן כי אמר נשיא
תוספת גדול הוא ולא גרסינן לה להא מלתא כי בספרים מדויקים כתיב
מעבירים וגם במסורה גדולה במקום שמנויין שם כל ד', Kasheh be-einai she-mikach
ha-mikra ha-nizkar kan ki omar nisa tosfot gadol hu ve-lo garsinan lah
le-ha milta ki bi-sefarim meduyakim ketiv ma'avirim ve-gam ba-masora gedola be-makom she-menuyim
sham kol dalet, so רש"י Rashi says first of all in all
of our books it says מעבירים. Ma'avirim. Number two, in the מסורה,
Masora, right, the מסורה Masora writers, they did all, you know, in
what is it, sixth century, seventh century, they did a whole counting
of every single letter in תנ"ך. Tanakh. He says if you look
there too, this is, they count all the places that לא כתיב
בהן יוד וקרין ולא מנה זה, lo ketiv bahen yud ve-karyin ve-lo
mana zeh, that this isn't in the list of things that's missing
a יוד. Yud. Okay, then anyway, so then רש"י Rashi goes on.
Okay, so, so he has another explanation. תוספות Tosafot as well says
מעבירם כתיב הש"ס שלנו חולק על הספרים שלנו. Ma'aviram ketiv ha-shas she-lanu
cholek al ha-sefarim she-lanu. So תוספות Tosafot says, yeah, maybe our גמרא
Gemara had a different נוסח Nusach than we now have in our
תנ"ך, Tanakh, שכתוב בהם מעבירים וכן מצינו בירושלמי בשמשון וישפוט את ישראל
ארבעים שנה מלמד שהיו פלשתים יראים ממנו כ' שנה אחר מותו כמו
בחייו. she-katuv bahem ma'avirim ve-chen matzinu bi-yerushalmi be-shimshon va-yishpot et yisrael arba'im
shana melamed she-hayu pelishtim yere'im mimenu kaf shana achar moto kemo be-chayav.
So anyway, they have a whole דרשה Derasha on that it says
פנחס, Pinchas, שמשון Shimshon was forty years. ובכל ספרים שלנו כתיב כ'
שנה, U-ve-chol sefarim she-lanu ketiv kaf shana, but in ours it doesn't,
that's a יוד Yud issue. In our תנ"ך Tanakh it says twenty
years, but the ירושלמי's Yerushalmi had it said forty years. So there
actually is some differences in the תנ"ך Tanakh of the בבלי Bavli
and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi from our תנ"ך. Tanakh. It's pretty funny that
רש"י Rashi here all of a sudden is protesting the יוד Yud
because רש"י Rashi in a, there's a couple of רש"י's Rashi על
התורה al ha-Torah that actually are against the מסורה, Masora, like a
recent רש"י Rashi where it says פילגשים, pilegshim, רש"י Rashi says that
it's, you know, it's חסר יוד, chaser yud, and in ours it's,
it has the יוד. Yud. Anyway, רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot are
both aware that the גמרא's Gemara text is not the same as
our תנ"ך Tanakh in these פסוקים. Pesukim. Okay, so now the גמרא...
Gemara...
wait, wait, wait, one quick question, but wasn't there also another sin
about, like, you know, taking the, forget about sleeping with the women,
but there was about like the fork and then taking the raw
meat...
Alright, so maybe that one they're not saying, but, but this one,
which obviously is seen as, you know, the most, the most severe,
is the one that they're saying, you know, did not really happen,
or at least by both, or רבא Rava is saying at least
פנחס. Pinchas.
So when you say חטאו Chat'u you mean...
Specifically, yeah, we're not saying none, we're saying the specific ones we're
talking about. That'll come up again as well. אמר רב שמואל בר
נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, Amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan,
so similar statement of רב שמואל בר נחמני Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani
in the name of רבי יונתן, Rabbi Yonatan, כל אומר בני שמואל
חטאו אינו אלא טועה. Kol omer benei Shmuel chat'u eino ela to'eh.
If you say the sons of שמואל Shmuel sinned, you're only making
a mistake. שנאמר, She-ne'emar, ויהי, Vayehi, if you look at the side
it's the, again, talk about differences in the way it is in
the גמרא Gemara and in our גמרא Gemara and in our text,
ויהי כאשר זקן שמואל ולא
הלכו בניו בדרכיו, Vayehi ka-asher zaken Shmuel ve-lo halchu banav bi-drachav, okay,
so,
so
it's as opposed to what it has ובניו לא הלכו, u-vanav lo
halchu, it's ולא הלכו בניו. ve-lo halchu banav. So again, interesting those
differences in the גירסא. Girsa. Anyway, בדרכיו. Bi-drachav. So they didn't go
in his way. בדרכיו הוא דלא הלכו הא מיחטא נמי לא חטאו.
Bi-drachav hu de-lo halchu ha me-cheta nami lo chat'u. Fine, they weren't
as פרום Frum as him, they weren't as big of a צדיק,
Tzaddik, they didn't go in his ways, but they, but you couldn't
say they sinned. Then you would have just had to say they
didn't follow his ways. It would have been a much harsher
indictment. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מה אני מקיים, Ela mah
ani mekayem, so what do you do with the end of the
פסוק, Pasuk, ויטו אחרי הבצע, Vayitu acharei ha-batza, that they went after
the, you know, the,
bribery and, and
after profit? So it doesn't mean that they actually took bribes. What
it means is שלא עשו כמעשה אביהם. She-lo asu ke-ma'aseh avihem. They
didn't do like their father did. שהיה שמואל, She-hayah Shmuel, the צדיק,
Tzaddik, what did שמואל Shmuel use to do? He would be מחזר
בכל מקומות ישראל. mechazer be-chol mekomot Yisrael. He would go on a
whole circuit, it's very explicit in the פסוקים, Pesukim, throughout all of,
all of the land of Israel, ודן אותם בעריהם. ve-dan otam be-areihem.
He would, you know, be a doctor, he would be a judge
that made house calls. He would go to each city. שנאמר והלך
מדי שנה בשנה וסבב בית אל והגלגל והמצפה ושפט את ישראל, She-ne'emar
ve-halach midai shana be-shana ve-savav beit el ve-ha-gilgal ve-ha-mitzpeh ve-shafat et Yisrael,
the whole circuit. והם לא עשו כן. Ve-hem lo asu chen. They
decided, uh, that's too much work. We're not going to do that.
אלא ישבו בעריהם. Ela yashvu be-areihem. They sat in their cities. They
say you come to us. כדי להרבות שכר לחזניהם ולסופריהם. Kedei le-harbot
sachar le-chazanehem u-le-sofereihem. Now, why? It's not just that they're lazy. It
has to fit in the פסוק Pasuk that says בצע Batza which
means like profit or wealth. כדי להרבות שכר לחזניהם ולסופריהם. Kedei le-harbot
sachar le-chazanehem u-le-sofereihem.
They had all of, you know, the people that they had to
patronage. You know, they had the חזנים, chazanim, the people that they
had to go that, that would be hired to go bring people
to the court and send out court notices, and especially if you're
bringing the people, if the people are coming to you, so then
you, you know, you have to have a whole entourage that is
helping that process. וסופריהם, U-sofereihem, the people that record the issues of
the court. So if you go from city to city, then you
maybe have to hire local talent. But so by staying where you
are, you can have your own patronage and therefore it is seen
as this issue of בצע. Batza. Now, that's actually very interesting because
I just came from a whole conference yesterday at the AJC which
was all about, you know, the issues around the Chief Rabbinate in
Israel and all of the many, many problems associated with it. Anyway,
but one of the issues that were brought up, which I would
have put pretty like low
not just blatant corruption,
but also just a lot of incompetence, which leads to a lot
of people suffering and injustice as well. So that's what the גמרא
Gemara is saying is they didn't want to be bothered, they wanted
to stay, and also it allowed them to have some patronage and
give people certain jobs, yes.
This is not a new problem. We talk about the Exilarch and
how the Exilarch has been screwing up a lot, and the Exilarch
isn't even named in here, he's considered so...
right. Well, we're going to get back to him a little bit
later, but yes, that is true.
So then ויטו אחרי הבצע?
vayahtu acharei
habatza?
They were interested in profit and
they did things that would help in terms of the intake of
money. Not necessarily that they took bribes, but that if they were
unconcerned with money, then they would have at their own expense gone
from city to city, been selfless and so on. But they weren't,
they had an interest in their bank account, they had an interest
in their friends' bank account, and therefore they sat where they were
and that helped.
Okay, ויטו אחרי הבצע וגו'?
vayahtu acharei
habatza v'go?
They perverted the
judgment.
Okay, so that's a good point. So according to this approach, it's
like I said, once you're concerned about that even if you're not
taking an outright bribe, it leads to incompetence, it leads to compromising
your standards, consciously or not consciously, and it leads to injustice. And
I think that's exactly the point being made here. So you see,
I mean, it's two ways to look at this גמרא. Gemara. You
can focus on the fact that it's papering over, but the other
thing to focus on, which I think is the very positive message
is, look what it's saying about even these small things, look at
how they lead
to very weighty consequences. And so, and that's certainly what's being said
here. So let's see as the גמרא Gemara continues. You know the
story which was when what's his name, I think it was what's
his name, not רב גורן, Rav Goren, but anyway, somebody, I think
it was when רב גורן Rav Goren was the Chief Rabbi, there
was this interest about trying to reconstitute the סנהדרין Sanhedrin in Israel.
So somebody said to him, I don't think it was רב גורן,
Rav Goren, but anyway, but somebody said to him, says look,
חכמים נבונים, chachamim nevonim, you know, that like the criteria in the
פסוקים pesukim about the סנהדרין Sanhedrin says that I know, that maybe
you can find. But שונאי בצע, sonei batza, where are you going
to get שונאי בצע? sonei batza? It says with enough money you
can get anything.
בן גוריון! Ben-Gurion!
Oh wow, okay, much earlier then.
I don't even know if it was בן גוריון, Ben-Gurion, I think
it was the Minister of
Education or something, anyway, I'm not sure exactly who it was.
Or Rabbi Maimon was part of an effort to...
yeah, okay, let's go on. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, so it says like
this. תניא. tanya. Now we're going to see not everybody agrees like
this. This is a מחלוקת
תנאים. machloket tana'im. ויטו אחרי הבצע. vayahtu acharei habatza. רבי מאיר אומר
חלקם שאלו בפיהם. Rabbi Meir omer chelkom sha’alu befihem. It is more
blatant, taking money for themselves. Now, not necessarily a bribe, but they
were לויים. Levi'im. So they would go to somebody and say, I
want my מעשר. ma'aser. Now, you're supposed to have the opportunity to
give your מעשר ma'aser who you want to, but if the judge
comes to you and says I want you to give me my
מעשר, ma'aser, you don't have much of a choice. So they misused
their positions of authority not by outright theft, but by demanding their
מעשר ma'aser from people who otherwise would not necessarily have given it
to them. רבי יהודה אומר מלאי הטילו על בעלי בתים. Rabbi Yehuda
omer melai hitilu al ba’alei batim. They gave basically their money to
invest to homeowners, meaning they basically said here you invest my money
for me, they gave it to a businessman, and then they made
a lot of money off of that. So maybe it's a certain
abuse of their position to get free investment advice or assistance from
these people, yes. And number two, as רש''י Rashi says is, is
that then when that person comes for you for a court case,
you're obviously going to look at him, judge him a little bit
differently. So maybe again, it wasn't an outright bribe, but certainly it
was inappropriate. רבי עקיבא אומר קופה יתירה של מעשר נטלו בזרוע. Rabbi
Akiva omer kupah yeteirah shel ma’aser natlu bizroa. They demanded an extra
box of מעשר ma'aser which seems pretty similar to the previous position.
This is a bit of a tease,
so he was a לוי? Levi? Yes.
רבי יוסי אומר מתנות נטלו בזרוע. Rabbi Yosi omer matanot natlu bizroa.
That again, all these seem to be a variation of the same
point: they demanded their gifts, they demanded their מעשר. ma'aser. Okay, maybe
different degrees of to what degree they forcefully did or sort of
just their position demanded it. Anyway, none of the, so it's interesting
that even these are saying it wasn't an outright bribe. But again,
I think that
you can really hear a very powerful lesson because that's how we
rationalize this, oh it wasn't outright theft, it wasn't this, but very
nice, but an abuse of your position of power and authority and
a way of doing these types of things about leading to money
that you don't deserve to have or to patronage or to other
ways of compromising your integrity, all this is the פסוק pasuk is
not letting you get off the hook. Is there an idea for
a דיין dayan in a גמרא Gemara like if somebody
has
personal interest they don't sit on the? Right, they... Right, right. If
you have a vested interest, yeah, you don't sit on the... absolutely,
if you're an נוגע בדבר, nogea b'davar, right, then you can't sit
on the case. אמר רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, Amar
Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, now we're moving on, כל
האומר דוד חטא אינו אלא טועה. kol ha'omer David chata eino ela
to'eh. Now דוד David with בת שבע. Batsheva. Now of course, you
know, the גמרא Gemara says that
later it will say that there were no other sins and we'll
talk about that, but at this stage it's not saying he did
no sins, right? There was a whole thing about the census, there
were a couple of sins by דוד, David, but it's saying the
sin of בת שבע Batsheva to say that that was a sin
of adultery, you're making a mistake. Okay, why? שנאמר, She'ne'emar, ויהי דוד
לכל דרכיו משכיל והשם עמו. Vayehi David l'chol drachav maskil v'Hashem imo.
All his ways, you know, he was wise and God was with
him, or successful. Well, it's a good question. אפשר חטא בא לידו
ושכינה עמו? Efshar cheit ba l'yado u'Shchina imo?
Right, he should do such a sin and God would stay with
him? אלא מה אני מקיים, Ela ma ani mekayem, מדוע בזית את
דבר השם לעשות הרע? Madua bazita et dvar Hashem la'asot hara?
Why did you, you know, denigrate the word of God to do
this evil? שביקש לעשות ולא עשה... She'bikesh la'asot v'lo asa... לעשות הרע.
la'asot hara.
You desired to do it, but you didn't
actually—I mean, you slept with בת שבע, Batsheva, but it wasn't actually
adultery. You would have committed adultery, but you managed to do it
without doing adultery. How's that possible? So first, before we find out
how that's possible, again, the question is are there, you know, are
there other voices? So we saw other voices about ראובן, Reuven, we
saw other voices about
בני—about bnei everyone, by the way, so far has had another voice.
ראובן Reuven really sinned, רב Rav said, even if פנחס Pinchas didn't
sin, חפני Chofni did the real sin the תורה Torah assigns to
them and פנחס Pinchas was held accountable because he didn't intervene. By
בני שמואל, Bnei Shmuel, we said that, you know, maybe they really
was direct taking of money, maybe again under some rationalization, but it
was a direct taking of money. And here, by דוד, David, let's
see how the גמרא Gemara responds to this idea that דוד David
did not sin.
אמר רב, Amar Rav, רבי Rebbi דאתי מדוד—רבי who was a descendant
of
דוד—מהפך ודורש בזכותיה דדוד. He's trying to defend דוד. David So it's
interesting, without exactly saying that דוד David. did sin, he's saying yes,
very nice, רבי Rebbi is trying to defend דוד. David Now remember
רב Rav was also the one that said that פנחס—פנחס didn't sin
but חפני Chofni did. So רב Rav is not letting these people
off the hook as easily as others. Anyway, רבי, Rebbi, he's coming
from דוד, David. he's trying to defend דוד. David, To דוד, David.
מדוע בזית את דבר השם לעשות הרע? madua bazita et dvar Hashem
la'asot hara? So now quoting another ברייתא: braita: why did you denigrate
the word of God to do evil? רבי אומר: Rebbi omer: משונה
רע זו מכל רעות שבתורה. meshuna ra zu mi'kol ra'ot she'ba'Torah. Here
where it says evil, it's different than other places it says evil
in the תורה. Torah. שכל רעות שבתורה כתיב בהו ויעש. She'kol ra'ot
she'ba'Torah ktiv behu vaya'as. Everywhere else it says he did the evil.
Very often by the kings in מלכים Melachim it says ויעש הרע
בעיני השם, vaya'as hara b'einei Hashem, right, he did the evil. Here
it doesn't say ויעש, vaya'as, here it says וכאן כתיב לעשות, v'kan
ktiv la'asot, 'to do', in the—what do you call it—infinitive, right?
Infinitive? שביקש לעשות ולא עשה. She'bikesh la'asot v'lo asa. He wanted to
do, but he did not actually do. Okay, now we're going to
have to explain how that's possible. את אוריה החתי הכית בחרב. Et
Uriah HaChitti hikita va'cherev. So you—now the פסוק pasuk says—so that's בת
שבע, Batsheva, we'll get back to her in a minute. But now
אוריה, Uriah, you're responsible for his death, you smote him by the
sword. Not literally, but he sent him into battle in order to
die. שהיה לך לדון בסנהדרין ולא דנתו. She'haya l'cha ladun b'Sanhedrin v'lo
danto.
That—why are you held—not because you really are held liable for killing
him. He deserved to die. We'll see in a minute that the
גמרא Gemara is going to say that he was מורד במלכות, mored
b'malchut, he rebelled against the authority of the king. And that is
deserving of death. So therefore he did deserve to die. Your sin
was that you did not do it in a court, but you
did it sort of extra-legally. But he did deserve to die.
Okay. ואת אשתו לקחת לך לאשה. V'et ishto lakachta l'cha l'isha. And
you took his wife for you as a wife. שלקוחים יש לך
בה. She'likuchin yesh l'cha ba. But actually marriage was binding with her.
Marriage was binding with her once אוריה Uriah died. But it was
binding with her even—even before, even when you slept with her the
first time, she was technically no longer married to אוריה. Uriah. Why?
דאמר רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, D'amar Rav Shmuel bar
Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, so notice it's the same רב שמואל בר
נחמני Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani in the name of רבי יונתן Rabbi
Yonatan who said דוד David, didn't sin. Here he's going to explain
how not. כל היוצא למלחמת בית דוד, Kol hayotzei l'milchemet Beit David,
anybody who would go out to a war at the time of
דוד, David כותב גט כריתות לאשתו, kotev get kritut l'ishto, he would
give his wife a divorce. What?
Yes, he would give her a גט, get, he said.
Yes, to give her a גט. get. So the גמרא Gemara is
going to say he gave her a גט. get. So it says
anybody that would go out to war would write a גט get
to his wife because maybe you wouldn't return from battle and nobody
would know if you're dead or not. So you would have a—you
would give a גט get upfront. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, ואת עשרת חריצי החלב
האלה תביא לשר האלף. v'et aseret charitzei hachalav ha'eleh tavi l'sar ha'elef.
Bring this—when ישי Yishai sends דוד David, to the brothers who are
out by, you know, with גלית, Goliath, out in the battlefield, he
says
that... these ten cakes of
cheese to the general, to the head of the thousand, ואת אחיך
תפקד לשלום, ve'et achecha tipkod leshalom, visit your brothers, check after their
welfare, ואת ערובתם תקח, ve'et aruvatam tikach, take their ערובה, aruvah, which
could mean like collateral. What does ערובה aruvah mean? So the גמרא
Gemara says, מאי ערובתם? mai aruvatam? So תני רב יוסף, tani Rav
Yosef, דברים המעורבים בינו לבינה, devarim hame'uravim beino leveina, something that intertwines
him to her, meaning the marriage. So take something that will free
them from their marriage. Take their גט. get. They forgot. They were
in such a rush, they left without giving their wives a גט.
get. Take גטס gets for them for their wives in order that
in case they don't come back, their wives will be free. So
that happened by אוריה, Uriah, and therefore בת שבע Bas Sheva was
technically not married at the time. Now, now,
there's an interesting debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos whether they
gave the גט get unconditionally, which is what תוספות Tosafos says. Of
course, then the problem is that what about the כהנים? Kohanim? Well,
I guess it's a good thing that כהנים Kohanim didn't go to
war. So okay, fine. And רש"י Rashi says, רש"י Rashi says they
gave it on a condition. But תוספות Tosafos is a little bit
bothered because if it's conditional, then as long as the condition isn't
satisfied, then it is like committing adultery. So תוספות, Tosafos, or might
be according to certain opinions, what is that status while it's being
held in abeyance and the condition isn't met? So that's one issue.
But now we'll get to the question about him being a מורד
במלכות, mored bemalchus, which allowed so that's how we get out of
adultery. Today you said
conditional גיטין. gittin. Right, exactly. Be wonderful. Yeah. Conditional marriage, this was
a conditional גט, get, but yeah, that is true. So the גמרא
Gemara says תני tani but
it makes them married until
right.
So that right, one of the עגונה agunah suggestions of dealing with
the עגונה agunah is conditional marriage, but the other suggestion, the other
suggestion רבקה Rivka is right, is no, the marriage is fine, but
then you have a conditional גט. get. And it's actually not a
conditional, maybe some say that you give the גט get right now
on condition, but I think some but the other suggestion is that
you appoint a שליח shaliach to write and give a גט get
now and then that and then he will do it, you know,
when certain conditions are met. Right, but I'm saying but that's a
little different than a conditional גט. get. A conditional גט get is
actually handing the גט get and saying it will take effect. But
you're right, those are suggestions that are raised right, right, not to
do with. Right, those are suggestions that have been raised for the
עגונה, agunah, absolutely. Okay, so yes, but what
about נתן Natan comes to him and he says I sinned?
Yes, so I sinned because, you know,
it was so you were playing around. I mean, what he was
saying is technically it wasn't a transgression, but obviously a lot of
not kosher stuff was being done here, the way he manipulated the
whole situation and so on. Let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara
will continue. I mean, it's like everything else, we're saying he's being
held accountable as if he sinned, but it's not, you know, but
it's not technically the sin itself. But let's take a look. I
want to read a little bit more about this because first we
have okay, בת שבע Bas Sheva she had a גט. get. How
about אוריה? Uriah? He got him killed. So let's take a look.
ואותו הרגת בחרב בני
עמון. ve'oto haragta becherev bnei Amon. Him you killed with the sword
of בני עמון bnei Amon because you sent him out to battle.
So מה חרב בני עמון אי אתה נענש עליו, ma cherev bnei
Amon ee ata ne'enash alav, the same way people that, you know,
when the sons of when בני עמון, bnei Amon, when this foreign
nation kills people, that's not your responsibility. אף אוריה הכי אי אתה
נענש עליו. af Uriah hachi ee ata ne'enash alav. So it's like
you killed him like everybody else that was killed by the בני
עמון, bnei Amon, meaning it's not your responsibility that he was killed.
You won't be punished. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? So now, how do
you explain that? מורד במלכות הוה, mored bemalchus hava, because he rebelled
against the kingdom. דאמר ליה, de'amar lei, because he said to him,
ואדוני יואב ועבדי אדוני על פני השדה חונים. vadoni Yoav ve'avdei adoni
al pnei hasadeh chonim.
My master יואב Yoav and the servants of my master are by
are on the, you know, out in the battlefield, how should I
go home to my wife if all of my, you know, all
of my fellow soldiers are out there fighting the war? So where's
this מורד במלכות? mored bemalchus? So רש"י Rashi says it's מורד במלכות
mored bemalchus because in the presence of דוד David he refers to
יואב Yoav as his master, which means that he has greater, you
know, he he you know his first allegiance is to יואב Yoav
rather than to דוד. Dovid תוספות Tosafos says that it's because he
refused to listen to דוד. Dovid. דוד Dovid. says go home to
your wife and he said I can't go home to my wife.
And now the גמרא Gemara here is not developing this idea of
מורד במלכות mored bemalchus and another גמרא Gemara does and learns it
out from the beginning of ספר יהושע Sefer Yehoshua where the people
say to יהושע, Yehoshua, כל אשר
ימרה פיך...
kol
asher yamreh picha...
יומת, yumat, something like that. Right, so anyway, right, so it's interesting,
we learn a הלכה halacha of מורד במלכות mored bemalchus from what
the people say to יהושע, Yehoshua, not anything God said, but we
learn from there that, you know, that he says if anybody disobeys
you he should be put to death, this principle of מורד במלכות.
mored bemalchus. Now what's interesting is that the גמרא Gemara says okay,
so the sin was he didn't deal with it in a סנהדרין,
Sanhedrin, which is interesting because you would have thought that the idea
of מורד במלכות mored bemalchus is like extra-legal, meaning it's not working
within the normal court system, right? It's the king's authority independent from
the court system and it doesn't have to be subject to the
court. So if you look at תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos says שהיה
לך לדונו בסנהדרין, shehaya lecha leduno besanhedrin, קשיא לרי, kashya leRi, דבפרק
קמא דמגילה אמרינן. deveperek kama deMegilla amrinan. גבי נבל דמורד במלכות לא
בעי מידייני, gabei Naval de'mored b'malchut lo ba'ei midainei, that you don't
have to judge a
מורד במלכות. mored b'malchut. It's extra-legal. ואוריה מורד במלכות הוה גמר סופו.
v'Uriya mored b'malchut havah gmar sofo. ויש לומר דברי צריך לדון v'yesh
lomar d'bari tzarikh ladun ולדעת אם היה מורד במלכות. v'lada'at im haya
mored b'malchut.
No, actually, you do have to at least prove and determine that
he was a מורד במלכות mored b'malchut and that has to be
done in a system of in a court of law. The king
cannot on his own act completely extra-legally. אבל לעניין לעיין בדיניה ולעשות
הלנת הדין, aval l'inyan l'ayein b'dinei v'la'asot halanat hadin,
you don't have to do the whole process of דין, din, but
you need to go through the courts to prove the facts. Okay?
Other things that are part of the whole process of דין din
aren't necessary, but and that's a very nice point, because מורד במלכות
mored b'malchut gives the king extra-legal powers, right? The question then becomes
are you a country of laws or a country of men? How
much can the king operate outside of the law? So this גמרא
Gemara is saying that some part of that has to at least
be determined in a סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, and that's where דוד Dovid is
being found culpable.
Okay, what's also very topical?
Also very topical. In the news, right?
Oh, right. Good point.
Not actually in the United States. Oh, all right. Fine. All
right, everybody can mutatis mutandis fill in the blank with the. All
right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Let's see, the גמרא
Gemara continues. So it says like this: אמר רב. Amar Rav. So
רב Rav says, now remember, רב Rav was the one before that
said, oh, רבי Rebbi is defending דוד, David and רב Rav was
the one that said that
חפני דחטא. Chofni d'chata. So here let's see what רב Rav himself
says. אמר רב כי מעיינת ביה בדוד, Amar Rav ki me'aynat bei
b'David, when you look closely at the story of דוד, David, לא
משכחת ליה בר מדאוריה. lo meshkachat leih bar m'de'Uriya. You won't find
any sin except for the sin of אוריה. Uriya. So not only
is he saying that he didn't really do the sin of with
בת שבע, Bas Sheba, he's actually saying that there are no other
sins that he has
done. דכתיב רק בדבר אוריה החתי, de-khitiv rak bi-devar Uriya ha-Chitti, only
with the matter of אוריה החתי. Uriya ha-Chitti. So you look at
תוספות, Tosfos, תוספות Tosfos says קשיא דהאי מעשה דהסתה, kashya de-hai ma'aseh
de-hasata, how about the whole census? So he says ויש לומר דלא
חשיב ליה דלא הוי כל כך עון גדול. v'yesh lomar d'lo chashiv
leih d'lo havi kol kach avon gadol. Okay, maybe it wasn't it
didn't get to the level of this big type of a sin.
Okay, but again here even רב Rav who was sort of pushing
back, here he says that was the only sin was the sin
of אוריה. Uriya. So the גמרא Gemara says אביי קשישא, Abaye Kashisha,
אביי Abaye the elder, presumably not the normal standard אביי, Abaye, רמי
דרב אדרב. rami d'Rav a'Rav. He shows there's a contradiction of two
statements of רב. Rav. מי אמר רב הכי, Mi amar Rav hakhi,
did רב Rav really say that? והאמר רב קיבל דוד לשון הרע,
ve-ha'amar Rav kibel David lashon hara, דוד David, accepted לשון הרע. lashon
hara. So you see, it was not the only sin that דוד
David did. So the גמרא Gemara says we'll see in a minute.
קשיא. Kashya. That's difficult. So it is interesting that רב Rav is
this contrary voice that is holding these people accountable for these sins
that they are
attributed to have done, and he doesn't try to reinterpret it, but
here by דוד David there's a little bit of a go in
both directions. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is going to look
at this other thing about דוד David accepting לשון הרע. lashon hara.
So let's take a look.
גופא. Gufa. Let's look at that at that original statement. רב אמר
קיבל דוד לשון הרע, Rav amar kibel David lashon hara, דוד David
accepted לשון הרע. lashon hara. דכתיב ויאמר לו המלך איפה הוא. de-khitiv
va-yomer lo ha-melekh eifo hu. This is the story where דוד, David
King דוד, David, once he ascended to the throne, was looking for
any remnant of the house of שאול Shaul in order to do
for them good. And this person ציבא, Tziva, who was an attendant
of the house of שאול, Shaul, said, "Oh yes, יהונתן Yehonatan has
a son left and his name is מפיבושת." Mephibosheth. And he brings
מפיבושת Mephibosheth in and he basically gives him the whole all the
property of the house of שאול Shaul and he's very generous to
him. So the king said to ציבא, Tziva, "איפה הוא, eifo hu,
where is this son?" ויאמר ציבא אל המלך הנה הוא בית מכיר
בן עמיאל בלא דבר. va-yomer Tziva el ha-melekh hineh hu beit Machir
ben Ammiel b'Lo Devar.
He is in the house of מכיר בן עמיאל Machir ben Ammiel
in בלא דבר. Lo Devar. Presumably that was the name of a
place. וכתיב, U-khtiv, and it says, וישלח המלך ויקחהו מבית מכיר בן
עמיאל מלוא דבר. va-yishlach ha-melekh va-yikkachehu mi-beit Machir ben Ammiel mi-Lo Devar.
Okay, and he took him from this place. So the גמרא Gemara
says, now one minute, now the story goes on by the way,
not right then, but later when דוד David, is running away from
אבשלום, Avshalom, this same attendant ציבא, Tziva, as we'll see in a
minute,
tells דוד David that
מפיבושת Mephibosheth basically has betrayed you and abandoned you. So then דוד
David gives all the wealth to ציבא. Tziva. So he's going to
have accepted the לשון הרע lashon hara from ציבא. Tziva. So the
גמרא Gemara says מכדי, Mikhdi, let's take a look. חזיה דשקרא הוא.
chazyei d'shakra hu. דוד David already saw that ציבא Tziva was a
liar. Now where did he see that ציבא Tziva was a liar?
Because the way the גמרא Gemara reads it, בלא דבר b'Lo Devar
and מלוא דבר, mi-Lo Devar, because other גמרות Gemaros have that מפיבושת
Mephibosheth in ברכות, Berachot, that מפיבושת Mephibosheth was like דוד's David רבי
Rebbi and that he was a huge תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham.
So the גמרא Gemara says that he said that rather than saying
he is in a place ב be in a place of בלא
דבר, Lo Devar, that what ציבא Tziva was saying is, "He is
בלא דבר. b'lo davar. He has no word," meaning he has no
תורה. Torah. And דוד David's found him מלוא דבר, mi-lo davar, filled
with words, a huge תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. So the גמרא Gemara
says מכדי, Mikhdi, let's see. חזיה דשקרא הוא. chazyei d'shakra hu. He
saw already that ציבא Tziva was lying. היכי הדר אלשין עילויה, Heikhi
hadar alshin ilavei, when then ציבא Tziva went later and slandered him,
מאי טעמא קיבל מיניה, mai ta'ama kibel mineih, why did he accept
it? דכתיב, De-khitiv, where do we see that happen? ויאמר המלך ואיו,
va-yomer ha-melekh v'ayo, where is he? ואיו בן אדוניך. v'ayo ben adonekha.
He saw ציבא Tziva with carrying all these donkeys and he gave
this food to דוד. David He said, "I brought this all for
you." And he says, "And where is your master?" or the son
of your
master. And and then David says, and actually
more than that it says that he actually is waiting for you
to fall so that he can rise back up to becoming a
king, right, so he, you know, because he's a descendant of Saul,
so he's hoping that you will that you'll be completely that your
that your kingship will you know will be taken away and that
he will and that he will be able to take your place.
So David said I'm giving all of the property to you. He
believed it. Okay, so ומנא לן דקיבלה מיניה, umina lan de-kibleh minei,
how do you know he accepted לשון הרע? lashon hara? דכתיב de-ktiv
ויאמר המלך הנה לך כל אשר למפיבשת, vayomer ha-melech hineh l'cha kol
asher l'mefivoshet, here he granted him everything that was belonging to Mefivoshet.
ויאמר ציבא השתחויתי אמצא חן בעיניך אדוני המלך vayomer tziva hishtachaveiti emtza
chen b'eineicha adoni ha-melech and then he bows down says thank you
very much. Okay, ושמואל אמר, u-shmuel amar, so that's what Rav says,
we don't have an answer of why he accepted it, but Rav
says he accepted לשון הרע. lashon hara. ושמואל אמר לא קיבל דוד
לשון הרע. u-shmuel amar lo kibel david lashon hara. David did not
accept לשון הרע. lashon hara. דברים הניכרין חזא ביה. devarim hanikarin chaza
bei. He actually saw evidence, supporting evidence that Mefivoshet was not so
supportive of him. How do you know? דכתיב de-ktiv now here again
is after David has now Avshalom has been killed and David is
returning to the throne, so the story before was with the when
he believed the לשון הרע lashon hara was when David was running
away, here now David is returning to the throne, and it says
ומפיבשת בן שאול ירד לקראת המלך. u-mefivoshet ben shaul yarad likrat ha-melech.
Mefivoshet went to meet the king. לא עשה רגליו ולא עשה שפמו,
lo asa raglav v'lo asa sfamo, he had not like you know
bathed his legs or somehow you know or cut his mustache, he
was looking very disheveled. ואת בגדיו לא כיבס v'et begadav lo kibeis
וכתוב v'chtiv ויהי כי בא ירושלים לקראת המלך ויאמר לו המלך למה
לא הלכת עמי מפיבשת. vayehi ki va yerushalayim likrat ha-melech vayomer lo
ha-melech lama lo halachta imi mefivoshet.
Why did you not come with me when I was running away
from Avshalom? ויאמר vayomer he says אדוני המלך עבדי רמני. adoni ha-melech
avdi rimani. Anyway my servant betrayed me or
deceived me. כי אמר עבדך אחבשה לי החמור וארכב עליה ואלך אל
המלך כי פסח עבדך. ki amar avdecha echbeshah li ha-chamor v'erkav aleiha
v'eileich el ha-melech ki pise'ach avdecha. I said I will you know
load up my I will you know saddle my donkey and I'll
ride to you because I'm lame so I can't walk, I needed
the donkey, and he basically doesn't say what happened but presumably then
he went and he stole the donkeys so I had no way
of getting to you, so he tricked me. וירגל בעבדך אל אדוני
המלך, vayerageil b'avdecha el adoni ha-melech, and he therefore slandered me your
servant to you my master the king. I was slandered and therefore
I didn't come to you because he stole the donkeys. ואדוני המלך
כמלאך האלהים, v'adoni ha-melech kemalach ha-elohim,
you my master the king are like an angel of God, ועשה
הטוב בעיניך, va'aseh ha-tov b'eineicha, do what is right in your eyes.
ויאמר לו המלך vayomer lo ha-melech and the king said to him
למה תדבר עוד דבריך. lama tedabeir od devarecha. You don't need to
speak anymore. אמרתי אתה וציבא תחלקו את השדה, amarti atah v'tziva techalku
et hasadeh,
split you know your inheritance. So that wasn't exactly
what you would have expected, you would have expected to completely reverse
it. ויאמר מפיבשת אל המלך, vayomer mefivoshet el ha-melech, Mefivoshet said to
the king גם את הכל יקח אחרי אשר בא אדוני המלך בשלום
אל ביתו, gam et hakol yikach acharei asher ba adoni ha-melech b'shalom
el beito, since you came home in peace nothing else matters to
me, only your wellbeing matters to me. Take it all. Sounds exactly
like Shlomo and dividing the kid, no let him have it all,
let him have it all, you're the real you're my real supporter.
So that's how you think the story ends, that he proved that
he was the true supporter of David. But let's see what the
Gemara does with this. The Gemara doesn't understand the connection of you
came back in peace let him have it all, so let's see
what the Gemara reads. The Gemara reads like this. אמר לו amar
lo so Mefivoshet said to David אני אמרתי מתי תבא בשלום, ani
amarti matai tavo b'shalom, I was so concerned about your wellbeing, when
would you come back in peace? ואתה עושה לי כך, v'atah oseh
li kach, and you're saying split the field? That's what that's what
I get back from you? I was so concerned about you, I've
always been a loyal follower. So לא עליך יש לי תרעומת, lo
alecha yesh li taromet, I don't have a complaint about you, אלא
על מי שהביאך בשלום, ela al mi sheheviacha b'shalom, my complaint is
about God, that God brought you back in peace. If that was
how you're going to act, who needs you? That's what the Gemara's
reading about Mefivoshet said to David. היינו דכתיב hainu de-ktiv ובן יהונתן
מריב בעל, u-ben yehonatan meriv ba'al, the son of Yehonatan was Meriv
Baal. וכי מריב בעל שמו והלא מפיבשת שמו, v'chi meriv ba'al shemo
v'halo mefivoshet shemo, was his name Meriv Baal? His name was Mefivoshet.
אלא מתוך שעשה מריבה עם בעליו, ela mitoch she'asah merivah im be'alav,
he made a fight with his master, meaning with
God. יצתה בת קול ואמרה yatzeta bat kol v'amerah נצא בר נצא,
natza bar natza, contentious one son of a contentious one. נצא דהתם,
natza dehatam, contentious because of what he did with you know with
he was angry at God after David treated him like that. ובר
נצא u-var natza דכתיב, de-ktiv, actually the grandson, ויבא שאול עד עיר
עמלק וירב בנחל, vayavo shaul ad ir amalek vayariv banachal,
he came to the to the wadi of Amalek or to the
city of Amalek
and he waged war in the wadi. So אמר רבי מני amar
rabbi mani על עסקי נחל, al iskei nachal, on the issues about
the wadi. So this is a very famous Gemara in Yoma that
says that Shaul said to God, God, how do you expect me
to wipe out Amalek? Even if there's one person who you know
for one person who you don't know who's the murderer, you say
one innocent death, you say you do this whole process of the
עגלה ערופה eglah arufah and here you know all these innocent people,
the children, the wives, the women and so on, how am I...
So then it says a heavenly voice came out and said אל
תהי צדיק הרבה, Al tehi tzadik harbeh, and you know, and then
he went in the end so he was מרחם על אכזרים סוף
שיתאכזר על רחמנים. merachem al achzarim sof sheyitchazer al rachmanim. How’s that
go? How’s the whole story by שאול? Shaul? Anyway, we’ll discuss that
when we get to that in יומא, Yoma, so wait a few
months. Anyway, but for now, anyway, the point is that שמואל Shmuel
had טענות tainos against God—not שמואל, Shmuel,
שאול Shaul had טענות tainos against God. מפיבושת Mefiboshet had טענות tainos
against God. So there they are both being held sort of in
contempt. Now,
this—so therefore what שמואל Shmuel is saying is that the only reason
דוד David. in the end accepted the slander was based on this
story in the גמרא, Gemara, meaning if you believe that that's what
happened, that מפיבושת Mefiboshet then said, "Ah, you know, if that's how
you're going to treat me, I wish you never had come back,"
you know, that then דוד Dovid said, "Oh, so I see you
never really were such a great supporter," and that, you know, and
that allowed him to support his decision. Of course, the problem was,
was that happened way after the decision. He had already given it
all to גיחזי—so Geichazi to—not גיחזי, Geichazi, to—what's-his-name, ציבא. Ziva.
So, you know, רש"י Rashi says, "Well, he gave it, but he
gave it when he was running away from, you know, from אבשלום."
Avshalom.
So his gift wasn't really meaningful. A king that's running away and
that's being dethroned, there's no power to it. So the power came
here. Okay, but still, the whole rest of the story, he's first
split it and then the rest of the story happens. Yeah, but
you know, but because he was disheveled, there was—it seemed like there
was evidence that he might not have really been such a supporter
of דוד. Dovid So anyway, the way שמואל Shmuel wants to read
it is, is that the decision wasn't finalized until he had some
supporting evidence. Okay, so now the גמרא, Gemara, having been focused on
דוד Dovid. accepting לשון הרע, lashon hara, is now focusing on מפיבושת
Mefiboshet and ציבא Ziva and on their wrongdoings. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says: אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav, בשעה שאמר דוד למפיבושת אתה וציבא תחלקו את השדה. besha'ah she'amar
Dovid leMefiboshet atah veZiva techaleku es hasadeh. But now going back and
focusing on דוד, Dovid that by דוד Dovid, splitting the field, that
was the wrong decision. That he—he should have realized that ציבא Ziva
was lying. He should have given it all to מפיבושת Mefiboshet and
that was the wrong decision. And at that moment, remember, this is
רב Rav who said that it was לשון הרע lashon hara without—there
wasn't supporting evidence. דוד Dovid just believed the slander without any supporting
evidence. At that moment, יצאה בת קול ואמרה, yatzah bas kol ve'amrah,
a heavenly voice came out and said: רחבעם וירבעם יחלקו את המלוכה.
Rechavam veYerovam yichaleku es hamalchus.
You split this field between a master and his servant, therefore, a
master and his servant, רחבעם Rechavam and ירבעם—right? Yerovam ירבעם, Yerovam, who
was a servant to רחבעם—right? Rechavam They will split the kingdom. And
that, you know, your own kingdom will ultimately be split. Again, it's
interesting because it evokes—we just mentioned שאול. Shaul. שאול Shaul comes back
from עמלק, Amalek, remember what שמואל Shmuel does? He rends the garment
and he says God has torn the מלכות malchus from you. So
here דוד Dovid as well, the מלכות malchus is going to be
torn and rendered into two, which is pretty, like, huge payback for
a sin of לשון הרע lashon hara that really had a consequence
of, you know, an issue of property and wealth. You know, so
again, here we're—the—until—you know, if
before we were saying it wasn't exactly the sin, the other part
of that of the theme was even small things count a great
deal. And here that certainly is what is being said. אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב אלמלי לא קיבל דוד לשון הרע לא נחלקו מלכות
בית דוד. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav ilmalei lo kibel Dovid lashon
hara lo nechleku malchus beis Dovid. If that had not happened, then
the kingdom never would have been split. ולא עבדו ישראל עבודה זרה.
velo avdu Yisrael avodah zarah. And what happened because the kingdom was
split? They erected the, you know, the
golden calves, you know, the two calves that were erected in the
territory of ישראל. Yisrael. And so they would not have worshipped עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. ולא גלינו מארצנו. velo galinu me'artzeinu. And it would
never have led to גלות. galus. All of this is because of
לשון הרע. lashon hara. So this is, you know, a real strong
warning about the possible consequences of believing slander. אמר שמואל בר נחמני
אמר רבי יונתן. Amar Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan. Now, back
to these statements about who didn't sin. כל האומר שלמה חטא אינו
אלא טועה. Kol ha'omer Shlomo chata eino ela to'eh. You say שלמה
Shlomo sinned, you're only—you're making a mistake. שנאמר ולא היה לבבו שלם
עם ה' אלוהיו כלבב דוד אביו. shene'emar velo hayah levavo shaleim im
Hashem Elokav kilvav Dovid aviv.
His heart was not—it wasn't wholehearted with God like דוד Dovid was.
כלבב דוד אביו הוא דלא הוי. Kilvav Dovid aviv hu dela havei.
It wasn't as wholehearted as דוד אביו. Dovid aviv. מיחטא נמי לא
חטא, Michta nami lo chata, but he didn't actually really sin. אלא
מה אני מקיים, Ela mah ani mekayem, what do I do with
the פסוק? pasuk? ויהי לעת זקנת שלמה נשיו הטו את לבבו, vayehi
l'eis ziknas Shlomo nashav hitu es levavo, that his wives, you know,
caused his heart to go astray. And it says they worshipped עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. What do you do with that? Says the גמרא
Gemara says: ההיא כרבי נתן. Hahi kerabi Natan.
That's like רבי נתן. Rabbi Natan. רבי נתן רמי, Rabbi Natan rami,
כתיב ויהי לעת זקנת שלמה נשיו הטו את לבבו. ksiv vayehi l'eis
ziknas Shlomo nashav hitu es levavo. One verse says that his wives
led his heart astray. וכתיב, vechsiv, the other פסוק pasuk says: כלבב
דוד אביו, kilvav Dovid aviv, like we just made the דרשה. drasha.
כלבב דוד אביו הוא דלא הוי. Kilvav Dovid aviv hu dela havei.
He wasn't as great as דוד. Dovid מיחטא נמי לא חטא, Michta
nami lo chata, but he didn't actually sin. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar,
so how do you deal with the text like he did sin?
ויהי לעת זקנת שלמה נשיו הטו את לבבו ללכת אחרי אלוהים אחרים.
Vayehi l'eis ziknas Shlomo nashav hitu es levavo laleches acharei elohim acheirim.
We do like we did with the same דרשה drasha for דוד:
Dovid. in order to go worship other gods. ולא הלך. velo halach.
They tried to get him ללכת, laleches, for the purpose of going
and worshipping other gods, but he didn't actually do the עבודה. avodah.
See one minute the verse says אז יבנה שלמה במה לכמוש שקוץ
מואב Az yivneh Shlomo bamah l'Chamosh shikutz Moav
Shlomo built an altar to this god of מואב Moav כמוש Kemosh
שביקש לבנות Shebikesh livnos אז יבנה Az yivneh in the future he
wanted to he was planning on it ולא בנה Velo banah he
didn't actually do it. It's interesting as anything. Okay to want to
do it. Yeah anyway yeah that's interesting because another גמרא Gemara says
that for all things מחשבה רעה אין הקדוש ברוך הוא מצרפה למעשה
Machshava ra'a ein Hakadosh Baruch Hu mitzarfa lema'aseh if you have evil
intentions God does not make it as if you've done it with
the exception of עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. So again the גמרא Gemara
is not getting him off the hook but it's just saying he
didn't go as bad as it sounds. אלא מעתה Ella me'ata so
alright אלא מעתה Ella me'ata
we'll get there.
אז יבנה יהושע Az yivneh Yehoshua so you say if the future
tense means he didn't do it what do you do with the
פסוק pasuk that says then יהושע Yehoshua יבנה yivneh literally will build
מזבח להשם? mizbeach l'Hashem? Would you say שביקש לבנות ולא בנה? Shebikesh
livnos velo banah? Would you say he wanted to but he didn't?
So you can't say יבנה yivneh means that he didn't do it.
אלא דבנה Ella debana
יהושע Yehoshua built it הכא נמי דבנה Hacha nami debana so שלמה
Shlomo built this. אלא כדתניא Ella kedetanya fine it's like we talked
in the ברייתא Braita here's how I know שלמה Shlomo didn't do
it. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yossi omer רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says
ואת הבמות אשר על פני ירושלים אשר מימין להר המשחית—actually Ve'et habamot
asher al pnei Yerushalayim asher miyamin l'Har HaMashchit our version's
משחית—so Mashchit the altars that were on the face of ירושלים Yerushalayim
on the right of the Mount of Olives אשר בנה שלמה מלך
ישראל Asher banah Shlomo Melech Yisrael which מלך שלמה Melech Shlomo built
לעשתרת שקוץ צידונים L'Ashtoret shikutz Tzidonim to Ashtoreth the god of the
Sidonians so here it says he actually built them so what are
you going to do with this פסוק? pasuk? אפשר Efshar so now
we're going to prove he couldn't really have built these why or
they couldn't really have been there why not because he was so
righteous but here's the proof. אפשר בא אסא—Asa Efshar ba Asa came
and he destroyed all the altars that were in
ישראל—ולא ביערם and he didn't destroy them? And then when יהושפט Yehoshaphat
came he destroyed all the altars that had cropped up since his
time ולא ביערם Velo bi'aram and he didn't destroy them? עד שבא
יאשיהו וביערם Ad sheba Yoshiyahu ubi'aram until יאשיהו Yoshiyahu came because the
פסוק pasuk we just quoted was that יאשיהו Yoshiyahu destroyed those altars
that שלמה Shlomo built. So who needed יאשיהו? Yoshiyahu? There were two
previous kings that destroyed all the altars. So obviously this could not
be taken literally. והלא כל עבודה זרה שבארץ ישראל אסא ויהושפט ביערום
Vehalo kol Avoda Zara shebe'eretz Yisrael Asa veYehoshaphat bi'arum אסא Asa and
יהושפט Yehoshaphat destroyed all the עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. The only reason
you needed another king to destroy it was because new things cropped
up but anything that was there before had been wiped out. So
it could not be that this was still around from the time
of שלמה. Shlomo. אלא מקיש ראשונים לאחרונים Ella makish rishonim l'acharonim
it connects the first people to the last people meaning שלמה Shlomo
is early and אחרונים acharonim is—not אסא Asa who is it? יאשיהו
Yoshiyahu yeah יאשיהו. Yoshiyahu.
מה אחרונים לא עשו ותלה בהן לשבח Mah acharonim lo asu vetala
bahen l'shvach
the same way יאשיהו Yoshiyahu didn't actually destroy those altars because as
we've said obviously those altars weren't really there anymore and nevertheless the
תורה Torah gives him credit for it because since he wanted to
get rid of all עבודה זרה Avoda Zara it's as if he
uprooted even the earlier altars. He gets credit for everything he would
have wanted to have done even if he didn't do it. אף
ראשונים Af rishonim similarly שלמה Shlomo לא עשו lo asu he didn't
really build those altars other people built them he allowed them to
be built ותלה בהן לגנאי Vetala bahen lignai but he's credited with
them. It's as if he built them he didn't himself build them
but it's as if he built them because he wanted them to
be.
So the next פסוק pasuk is וילך שלמה אחרי עשתרת אלהי צידנים
ואחרי מלכם שקץ עמנים
Vayelech Shlomo acharei Ashtoret elohei Tzidonim ve'acharei
Milcom shikutz Amonim he wanted to. Well what are you going to
do with this? הכתיב Hachtiv but doesn't it
say the phrase that we asked ויעש שלמה הרע בעיני ה' Vaya'as
Shlomo hara be'einei Hashem and so
he did evil? So now getting back to the theme of yesterday
אלא מפני שהיה לו למחות בנשיו ולא מיחה. Ella mipnei shehaya lo
limchot benashav velo micha. Maybe he didn't do it but he didn't
intervene he didn't stop it from being done. So you know Dave's
question earlier which I never got back to about you know King
David and he's being held obviously accountable and his child dies and
all of that so the גמרא Gemara can't say there היה לו
למחות haya lo limchot because that was him himself that he was
doing it it just says that he played all these tricks. So
there you know even according to the גמרא Gemara you have to
say obviously it doesn't mean that he was
you know innocent it's just that the way it's framing what he
did is there. Here though by שלמה Shlomo it's able to say
that his sin was that he could have intervened. מעלה עליו הכתוב
Ma'ala alav hakatuv so since he could have intervened and he didn't
כאילו חטא Ke'ilu chata it's as if he sinned. אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel נוח לו לאותו צדיק שיהא
שמש לדבר אחר. Noach lo l'oto tzadik sheyehei shamash l'davar acher. It
would have been better that that צדיק tzadik שלמה—interesting Shlomo now he's
being called a צדיק—would tzadik have actually done personally some service to
an עבודה זרה Avoda Zara that he would have like I don't
know sweeping up in the house of the of the pagan temple
that's what שמש לעבודה זרה shamash l'avoda zara means שמש לדבר אחר.
Shamash l'davar acher. ואל יכתב בו ויעש הרע בעיני ה' V'al yikatev
bo Vaya'as hara be'einei Hashem rather than saying he did the evil
which actually means that you know and it's very interesting how we
think about it right? We think you know I want to keep
my hands clean so as long as I'm not doing anything wrong.
So he says actually this gets back to our earlier theme of
accountable when you could intervene because he didn't intervene he's being held
accountable as if he did all these things and it's ויעש הרע
בעיני ה' Vaya'as hara be'einei Hashem and it would have been better
for him personally to sully his hands and not do real עבודה
זרה Avoda Zara but have been like an you know a janitor
in the house of an עבודה זרה Avoda Zara and that would
have been better than to have passively not intervened. and being held
accountable for all of this. So גמרא Gemara is really giving the
weight of what it means, you know, of the accountability of when
you could intervene and when you could protest and you don't. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara wrapping this up let's get to the
end says: אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel
oh wait did it just say that? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל
בשעה שנשא שלמה את בת פרעה, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel beshaah
shenasah Shlomo et Bat Paroh, when שלמה Shlomo married the daughter of
פרעה, Paroh, הכניסה לו אלף מיני זמר, hichnisah lo elef minei zemer,
she brought in a thousand types of musical instruments, ואמרה לו veamrah
lo and she said to him, כך עושים לעבודה זרה פלוני, kach
osin laavoda zara ploni, here's what you do for this עבודה זרה,
avoda zara, כך עושים לעבודה זרה פלוני, kach osin laavoda zara ploni,
here's what you do for that עבודה זרה, avoda zara, ולא מיחה
בה velo micha bah and he didn't protest, and therefore he is
held accountable for all of it. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל בשעה
שנשא שלמה את בת פרעה, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel beshaah shenasah
Shlomo et Bat Paroh, when he married בת פרעה, Bat Paroh, ירד
גבריאל ונעץ קנה בים, yarad Gavriel venaatz kaneh bayam, גבריאל Gavriel went
and put a stick in the middle of the ocean, ועלה בו
שירטון ונבנה בו כרך גדול שלו רומי, vealah bo sirton venivnah bo
krach gadol shelo Romi, and a sandbar formed around the stick,
and that ultimately led to the founding of Rome. Okay, because... so
this is actually I found in Steinsaltz it actually says that the,
you know, the sort of the, the Greek taking over the sort
of dominance over the Southern Italy happened right around the same time
of שלמה. Shlomo. The founding of Rome happened around 200 years later.
But anyway clearly this idea same way by דוד Dovid: accepting לשון
הרע lashon hara the מלכות malchus split, by שלמה Shlomo introducing עבודה
זרה avoda zara into the land of Israel and allowing this to
happen and allowing this external influence I would say of בת פרעה
Bat Paroh ultimately led the גמרא's Gemara understanding like to the Rome
which would be the destroyer of the temple which שלמה Shlomo had
built, so you see the parallel there, and in addition what I
would say is also since we're coming up to the חנוכה Chanukah
time, the external influence of Hellenism and so on I imagine is
part of this as well. Let's just finish, okay. במתניתא תנא, Bematnita
tana, in a ברייתא Baraita we taught, אותו היום שהכניס ירבעם שני
עגלי זהב, oto hayom shehichnis Yerovam shenei eglei zahav, so let's not
forget that ירבעם Yerovam was the one who actually began the עבודה,
avoda, you know, the institutionalized עבודה זרה, avoda zara, בבית אל אחד
ובדן, beBeis El echad ubeDan, one in בית אל Beis El and
one in דן, Dan, נבנה צריף אחד, nivnah tzrif echad, that on
that little island that was forming that was going to be, you
know, Rome or... so now actually it started being inhabited. A little
hut was built. That added the next stage of development. וזו היא
איטליא של יון, Vezo hi Italya shel Yavan, and this is Italy
of Greece, meaning when Greece sort of, you know, had dominance over
the southern part of Italy. Again Rome itself was a little while
later, but now you know first the, first the island was formed,
then they started building little huts, and all of this was as
we started sinning and you know and so ירושלים Yerushalayim goes down
and Rome goes up. אמר שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן: Amar
Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonasan: כל אומר יאשיהו חטא אינו אלא
טועה, Kol omer Yoshiyahu chata eino ela toeh, the last one, יאשיהו
Yoshiyahu sinned, he is nothing but mistaken. שנאמר, Sheneemar,
now who said יאשיהו Yoshiyahu sinned? Because he was a good guy.
But here's the problem. It says ויעש הישר בעיני ה' וילך בכל
דרך דוד אביו, vayaas hayashar beeinei Hashem vayelech bechol derech David aviv,
אלא מה אני מקיים, ela mani mekayem, so that's fine, so he
didn't sin. So what's the problem? No, it says וכמוהו לא היה
לפניו מלך אשר שב אל ה' בכל לבבו. vechamoho lo hayah lefanav
melech asher shav el Hashem bechol levavo. There was never a king
who returned to God, returned, where did he go? So it seems
like he had gone, he needed to do תשובה teshuva for something.
So no, it doesn't mean he needed to do תשובה. teshuva. So
what what did it mean he returned to God? שכל דיין שדן
מבן שמונה
עד שמונה עשרה החזירן להן, Shekol dayan shedan miben shemoneh ad shemoneh
esreh hechziran lahen, because basically he was king at eight and presumably
as king he sat in judgment, but eighteen years later, not when
he was eighteen, eighteen years later he reversed it. Why did he
reverse it? Not because he was a minor, he was king he
was allowed to judge. But because eighteen years later was when he
found the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. And then he realized oh my
God wait a minute I didn't apply the right דין, din, I
forgot about this whole ספר תורה Sefer Torah and תורה שבכתב Torah
she-be-ksav and תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-be-al-peh, so he reversed all his
judgments. That was שב אל ה'. shav el Hashem. Okay. שמא תאמר
נטל מזה ונתן לזה, Shema tomar natal mizeh venatan lezeh, maybe actually
took money away from ראובן Reuven and gave it to שמעון, Shimon,
a complete reversal so even the guy who had won before now
lost. תלמוד לומר בכל מאודו, Talmud lomar bechol meodo, all his strength
which means wealth, שנתן להן משלו. shenasan lahen mishelo. No, the people
he had awarded the, you know, the case to, they kept their
money, and then he made it up to the other person out
of his own pocket.
I guess he wasn't doing it in פשרות.
pesharos. Okay right. ופליגא דרב, Upliga deRav, דאמר רב: deamar Rav: אין
לך גדול בבעלי תשובה יותר מיאשיהו. ein lecha gadol bebaalei teshuva yoser
miYoshiyahu.
Again רב Rav is not so reluctant to say people sinned. So
he says no, יאשיהו Yoshiyahu was a big בעל תשובה, baal teshuva,
he started his life maybe as an עובד עבודה זרה oved avoda
zara like his father whatever, but he did תשובה. teshuva. בדורו, Bedoro,
he was in his generation the biggest בעל תשובה. baal teshuva. ואחד
בדורנו, Veechad bedoreinu, and there's one in our generation. Who is that?
You don't want to be listed, maybe you do, I don't know.
Oh you're a big בעל תשובה baal teshuva because you started... ומנו
הוא, Umanu hu, and who is he? אבא אבוה דרבי ירמיה בר
אבא, Abba avuha deRabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba, the father of רבי ירמיה
בר אבא. Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba. Okay. ואמרי לה, Vamrei lei, אחא,
Acha, interesting names, אחא אחוה דאבא אבוה דרבי ירמיה בר אבא, Acha
achua deAbba avuha deRabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba, so אחא Acha which was
the brother of the father of רבי ירמיה בר אבא. Rabbi Yirmiyah
bar Abba. Maybe these names are by the way, you know, changed
to protect the innocent like it's funny his father's name is אבא,
Abba, his father's brother's name is אחא. Acha. Anyway, דאמר מר deamar
Mar because מר Mar said, רבי אבא ואחא אחי הוו, Rabbi Abba
veAcha achi havu, so אבא Abba and אחא Acha were brothers. Okay.
אמר רב יוסף: Amar Rav Yosef: ועוד אחד בדורנו, veod echad bedoreinu,
there's another big בעל תשובה baal teshuva in our generation. Who is
that?
ומנו עוקבא בר נחמיה ריש גלותא. Umanu Ukva bar Nechemiah Reish Galusa.
Remember we mentioned מר עוקבא, Mar Ukva, so here you have the
ריש גלותא Reish Galusa again. But the ריש גלותא Reish Galusa yesterday...
Was said he's going to be judged in the hot, in the
scalding water because he was allowing certain amount of injustice and not
forbidding. Here he's saying that he was a big... in many different
ways. Yeah, but I think somebody says it's מר עוקבא. Mar Ukva.
Anyway, here it's saying that he was a big, that he was
a big בעל תשובה. ba'al teshuvah. והיינו נתן דצוציתא, v'hainu Nasan deTzitzisa,
and he was also called Nathan of the sparks, like maybe sparks
coming out of his head or ציצית, tzitzis, questions what that means.
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, הוה יתבינא בפרקא, hava yasvina b'pirka,
I was sitting in you know in the in the in the
learning that goes in the learning room in the learning, והוה קא
מנמנמי, v'hava ka menamnem, I was nodding off, וחזאי בחלמא, v'chazai b'chilma,
and here's what I saw in my dream as I was nodding
off during the learning session, דקפשי ידיה וקבליה, d'kapshi yadei v'kablei, a
hand came out from heaven and accepted this עוקבא בר נחמיה, Ukva
bar Nechemya, so he was a big בעל תשובה ba'al teshuvah and
ultimately his תשובה teshuvah was accepted by God. הדרן עלך בהמה. Hadran
alach Behemah. Okay.